A Guide to the Henry H. Hill Collection, 1908-1963, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Henry H. Hill Collection, 1908-1963, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Hill, Henry H. (Henry Harris Bunker)
Ms1980-003
1.0 Cubic Feet 5 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Mrs. Douglas Boynton of Roanoke, Virginia in May 1980. Additional materials (glass plate negatives) were donated in the early 2000s.
Biographical/Historical Information
A native of Scottsville, Virginia, Henry Harris (Bunker) Hill was associated with VPI as a student and professor for more than half a century. He received his B.S. in Chemistry in 1907, and his M.S. in the same subject in 1909. In 1907, Hill was appointed Assistant Chemist, and in 1913 Associate Chemist of the Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station. Before retiring from VPI in 1950, he served seven years as the head of the Agricultural Chemistry department.
Henry Hill was involved in the community, serving as Elder in the Presbyterian church, as well as being an officer in the Montgomery County Democratic Committee for several years. Hill also served as the Executive Secretary of the VPI Alumni Association, along with being the publicist for the Athletic Association.
Scope and Content
The Henry H. Hill collection consists of historical and genealogical research compiled by Hill during his lifetime in southwest Virginia. Research includes Hill biographical information (1941-50), Blacksburg history and Montgomery County (1798-1951, n.d.), VPI (1891, n.d.), Civil War history (1863-1963, n.d.), and genealogical information and biographical sketches (1821-1950, n.d.).
The collection is comprised almost exclusively of photocopies and typescripts, so the dates reflected above are from the original source of the typescript and not the actual dates of the material. The dates of the material are included in the contents list.
In addition, a collection of glass plate negatives and film negatives was donated in the early 2000s. These consist of campus views, images of footballs players/teams/events, cadet life, and images of individuals and art works.
Arrangement
In 2017, this collection was arranged into series based on the previous organzation by material types. Series I: Henry H. Hill Biographical Information includes a folder of biographical materials about Hill, created in the early 1940s. Series II: Blacksburg History and Montgomery County contains compliled research notes on local history, primarily photocopies. Series III: Virginia Polytechnic Institute includes research files on the history of the university, in particular, the case of three dismissed faculty members in 1891. This series also contains the collection of glass plate and film negatives. Series IV: Genealogical Information consists of photocopies and typscripts of research on a number of local/regional families, including, but not limited to: Appersons, Blacks, Prices, and Prestons. Series V: Subject Files is comprised of research materials (again, mostly photocopies and typescripts) realting to local Civil War history and other topics of interest to Hill.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Civil War; Faculty; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Series I: Henry H. Hill Biographical Information, 1941-1943, n.d.
  - Personal Files, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Biographical abstracts and copies of correspondence letters.
  - Draft of "Recollections of a Very Eventful Life," by H. H. Hill, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Blacksburg History and Montgomery County, 1936-1951, n.d.
  - Compiled notes on the history of Blacksburg (original typescript source date: 1798-1951), 1936-1951, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contents
    William Black's petition to the 1797 General Assembly (photocopy)
    Assembly Act establishing town (January 13, 1798)(photocopy of typescript)
    Letter from Joseph E. Penn to Harvey Black (1871)(photocopy of typescript)
    "In Old Blacksburg," by Dr. Conway (typescript of 1916 reprint)
    Notes from Mrs. Robinson's book "1833-1933" (photocopy of typescript)
    "Customers of a Blacksburg Store in 1866-68" (photocopy of typescript)
    Correspondence letters (1 original, 1936), typescripts of articles, and a newspaper article from the Montgomery News Messenger (1951) (photocopies)
    Miscellaneous items (photocopy of typescripts)
  - Notes on the Blacksburg Presbyterian Church (photocopies of typescripts), 1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Montgomery County, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Copy of the deed of Old St. Peter's (photocopy of transcript)
    Excerpt taken from "Mineral Resources of Virginia," by Thomas Leonard Watson. (typescript)
    "Issac Shelby, to his Uncle John," taken from the Draper Manuscripts (photocopy of typescript)
    Miscellaneous notes (2 items)(photocopies)
- Series III: Virginia Polytechnic Institute, 1895-1913, 1950-1952, n.d.
  - Charges and specifications concerning 1891 incidents involving three dismissed faculty members versus the VPI Board of Visitors (photocopies of transcripts), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Depositions in the 1891 case involving three dismissed faculty members versus the VPI Board of Visitors (128 p.), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - VPI (photocopies of typescripts), 1891, 1950-1952 (original typescript source date), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "History of the College" through 1891 (typescript)
    Notes on the Henderson Infirmary (typescript)
    Article: "Virginia Tech's 'Highty Tighties'" by H. H. Hill (photocopy)
    "The Virginia Tech Campus is Rich in Historic Memory" by H. H. Hill (photocopy of typescript)
    "The Marauding Cadet and the Presbyterian Pastor" (photocopy of typescript)
    Roster of the second Virginia Regiment Band (VPI Cadets) (photocopy of transcript)
    Correspondence letters (1950-1952)(photocopies)
  - Glass Plate Negatives & Negatives, 1895-1912, n.d.
    Arrangement
    Glass plates and negatives are of varying sizes and as a result, not all items depicting the same subjects could be placed together in the same boxes. The list below groups images by subjects and indicates the box-folder for each item. All items are glass plate negatives, unless otherwise noted in the title.
    - Cadets
      - Band, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Battalion of Cadets (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Cadet (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Cadet band (2 copies) (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
      - Cadets & Cannon (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Cadet Drill (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Campus
      - "Breaking Dirt for the Alumni Gate" (2 copies), 1912 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - "Bird's-Eye View of Grounds and Buildings" (2 copies) (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
      - Campus View (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Campus View (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Campus View-Farms (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Building Construction (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Construction [film negative] (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Construction (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Construction Workers (First Library?) (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Faculty Row/YMCA/Barracks/Academic Building (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Farm Building (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - First Library (3 different plates), Pre-1953 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
      - Preston and Olin Building, Pre-1913 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - (Preston and Olin?) Building (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "As the Shops looked in the Old Days" (Shops) (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Shops (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Snow Drift, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Snow Storm (3 different plates), 1895 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
    - Football
      - Football (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Football Player (Patrick?) (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Football Player in VAMC jersey (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Football Players with Puppy (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Football Players (2 different plates) (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
      - Football Players, Practice (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Football Practice [film negative] (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Football Team, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Football Team, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Football, Team of 1905 (3 copies), 1905 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
      - Football Team (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Football Team (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Two Football Players in VPI Jerseys (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - People
      - "Bunker" Hill, Price Hall, 1920s (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "Dad" (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Faculty (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - "Frith" [image of drawing] (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Olivia Tutwiler (later Hill) (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
      - Postcard (unidentified man (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - University Presidents Portraits (McBryde, Lomax, Minor, Buchanan, Conrad) (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Robert E. Lee Portrait (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Genealogical Information, 1821, 1939-1950, n.d.
  - Compiled genealogical information on the Lybrook and Apperson families (photocopies, typescripts), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Compiled genealogical information on the Black family (photocopies, typescripts), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Compiled genealogical information on the Price family (original typescript source date: 1944-48) (photocopies, typescripts), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Compiled genealogical information on the Preston family (original typescript source date: 1939-46)(photocopies, typescripts), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Biographical Sketches (original typescript source date: 1821, 1940-50)(photocopies of typescripts), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    J M. McBryde
    Harvey Lee Price
    Harvey Black
    "The Big Four"
    Colonel John Brown
    Brig. General William M. Browne
    Professor Jno. E. Christian
    William Christian - pension plea (1821)
    Major General Patrick R. Cleburne
    Brig. General Xavier B. Debray
    Francis Henderson
    E. B. Kinzer
    General James H. Lane
    Colonel Heros von Borcke
- Series V: Subject Files, 1863-1963, n.d.
  - Civil War (originial typescript source date: 1863-1963)(photocopies, typescripts), 1908, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    "The Battle of Cloyd's Mountain" (typescript)
    "My Horse Comet," by Lt. Col. W. W. Blackford (typescript)
    "Soldiers and Daughters of the Confederacy, including World War I and II soldiers buried in the Blacksburg Westview Cemetary" (photocopy of typescript)
    Newspaper article concerning McCormick's Civil War history (photocopy)
    John W. Mallet (1950)(photocopy of reprint)
    "Recollections of the Rebellion," by James C. Hill (1878)(photocopy of typescript)
    Excerpt from the diary of John S. Apperson (April 29 to May 7, 1863) (typescript)
    "Experiences as a Prisioner of War," by G. W. Finley (1908)(typescript)
    "The Impending Clash" (1935)(typescript)
    Miscellaneous notes and correspondence (photcopies of typescripts)
  - Miscellaneous (original typescript source date: 1942-1943, n.d.), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    "Recollections of Scottsville, 1870-1886," by John C. Hill (1943)(typescript)
    "John A. North House (Star Tavern)" (1942)(typescript)
    "The Star Spangled Banner and the Printer's Apprentice" (typescript)
    "The Praying Kernels" (typescript)